Brockton, Mass. Porter Congregational Church, 1800-1979.
Congregational Library Archives
Brockton, Mass. Porter Congregational Church, 1800-1979.
RG5395
Congregational Library Archives
2.01 Cubic Feet
(4 boxes)
The Porter Evangelical Church in North Bridgewater, later the Porter Congregational Church in Brockton, was established in 1850 by members who left the First Parish Congregational Church over ecclesiastical differences. The church purchased a building just north of the First Parish Congregational Church in 1851 and the building was further renovated in 1883, 1925, and 1950. The Wendell Avenue Church and Waldo Congregational Church were both formed out of area missions administered by the Porter Church. In 1980, the Porter Congregational Church merged with the First Parish Congregational Church, South Congregational Church, and Waldo Congregational Church to form the Christ Congregational Church in Brockton. This collection contains the administrative, financial, historical, and ministerial records of the Porter Congregational Church, as well as the records of many church groups. Included in the collection are vital membership records, church and society records, committee and group records, and correspondence.
Porter Congregational Church (Montello, Brockton, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Porter Congregational Church in 1980. Materials were sepparated out of RG0037 in March, 2019; Accession 2019-04.
Historical Note
During the 1840s, Rev. Paul Couch, minister at the First Parish Congregational Church in North Bridgewater, began to liberalize some of the more traditional teachings and traditions of the church. In response, some members of the church called for Rev. Couch to resign. Over the course of two years between 1948 and 1950, members of the liberal and orthodox wings of the church debated over Rev. Couche's position. Ultimately Rev. Couch did not resign and his continued service was maintained by the church. In response, approximately 70 names of persons interested in forming a new church were collected on February 12, 1850. An ecclesiastical council was called for March 6 and from that meeting the Porter Evangelical Church was formally gathered. John F. Norton was installed as the first minister of the church and stayed for a year. In 1852, Charles L. Mills was installed as pastor.
The newly formed congregation initially met at Tyler Cobb's Hall; their first meeting was held on March 10, 1850. In order to purchase land for a church, the Porter Society was formed on March 20, 1850. In 1851 the society purchased and renovated an old building on Main Street just north of the First Parish Congregational Church. In 1869 the top of the church spire was destroyed during a wind storm. The steeple was repaired in 1883 while the church itself underwent a major renovation and expansion project.
The Church Work Committee was formed in 1885. Its initial function was to assist the pastor and provide help to the Porter Church's parishioners. However that mission quickly expanded to include the management of Brockton area missions to provide sanctuary spaces for poor and disenfranchised citizens in the north-east of Brockton. Out of that mission both the Wendell Avenue Church, which began as the Wendell Avenue Chapel, and the Waldo Congregational Church, which began as the Montello Mission, were established in the mid-1890s.
At some point in the mid-1910s, the church name changed to The Porter Congregational Church. The church building was again renovated in 1925 as part of planned anniversary activities. The renovation also included the construction of a new steeple. The renovations also included the construction of a multi-purpose recreational building behind the church. There were further renovations completed in 1950 as part of the centennial celebrations. In 1980, the Porter Congregational Church merged with the First Parish Congregational Church, South Congregational Church, and Waldo Congregational Church to form the Christ Congregational Church in Brockton. The Porter Congregational Church building is now the headquarters for the Keys of The Kingdom Tabernacle of Prayer For All People, International.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the administrative, financial, historical, and ministerial records of the Porter Congregational Church, as well as the records of many church groups. The records also provide valuable context for the creation of the church out of a doctrinal dispute with the First Parish Congregational Church. Included in the records are record books of the church and parish, vital member records, financial records, records relating to the construction of the church, records of various church groups and the Sunday school, orders of worship, and ministerial correspondence.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the four series listed below. Within each series, materials have been arranged, primarily, in chronological order by start date, and secondarily, by topic.
Series 1: Church and society records, 1847-1979
Series 2: Financial and building records, 1800-1960
Series 3: Church committee and group records, 1850-1923
Series 4: Ministerial records and church services, 1800-1950
Related Materials
In 1980, the First Parish Congregational, South Congregational, Porter Congregational, and Waldo Congregational Churchs merged into a single entity, the Christ Congregational Church. The records of all four churches are held at the Congregational Library & Archives:
Brockton, Mass. First Parish Congregational Church records, 1738-1980.
Brockton, Mass. South Congregational Church, 1835-1979.
Brockton, Mass. Waldo Congregational Church, 1896-1980.
Bibliography
The book of the Chronicles of the Porter Congregational Church on the occasion of the One-Hundredth Anniversary 1950. Brockton: 1950. 17.11.1 B78.33 ChrCC
Baptismal records.; Church bells.; Church finance.; Church group work.; Church libraries.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Installation (clergy).; Pews and pew rights.; Sunday school music.; Sunday schools -- Records.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Brockton (Mass.) -- Church history.; Porter Congregational Church (Montello, Brockton, Mass.); Montello (Brockton, Mass.) -- Church history.; North Bridgewater (Mass.) -- Church history.; Waldo Congregational Church (Brockton, Mass.); Wendell Avenue Congregational Church (Brockton, Mass.)
- Church and society records, 1847 1979; 1847-1979; 21 Files; (8 volumes, 13 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the administrative records of both the church and parish, as well as vital membership records. Included in the series are record books for the church and parish that contain meeting minutes, records of votes, and membership records. Also included in the series are the records of the standing committee, annual reports, historical sketches, clippings, and records related to the genesis of the Porter Congregational Church.
  - Sepparation documents, 1847 1848; 1847-1848 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Church and parish records, 1850 1860; 1850-1860 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photostat church records, 1850 1861; 1850-1861 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Church records, 1850 1886; 1850-1886; 1850 1929; 1850-1929 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Church records, 1886 1906; 1886-1906 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Society records, 1850 1875; 1850-1875 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Correspondence, 1850 1939; 1850-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Doctrinal pamphlets, 1856 1872; 1856-1872 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1876 1971; 1876-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Standing Committee records, 1887 1901; 1887-1901 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Standing Committee records, 1901 1910; 1901-1910 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Standing Committee records, 1911 1923; 1911-1923 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Standing Committee records, 1923 1930; 1923-1930 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Register of members, 1887 1929; 1887-1929 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Annual reports, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 75th anniversary time capsul signatures, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Historical sketches, 1925 1975; 1925, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1969 1974; 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1975 1979; 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Membership lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Constitution and by-laws, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Financial and building records, 1800 1960; 1800-1960; 11 Files; (1 volume, 10 folders)
  This series contains records relating to the finances of the church as well as the records relating to construction and maintenance of the church building. Included in the series are financial ledgers, pew records, architectural drawings, and in-depth accounts of the money spent and collected to build the church building.
  - Memorial gifts, 1800 1950; 1800-1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pew deeds, 1827 1851; 1827-1851 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer's book, 1850 1877; 1850-1877 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Building committee records, 1850 1852; 1850-1852 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Construction account book, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Construction bills and receipts, 1850 1851; 1850-1851 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Account of contributions, 1850 1852; 1850-1852 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Purchase of bell, 1850 1854; 1850-1854 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Pew plan, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Financial records, 1857 1960; 1857-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Porter tower drawings, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Church committee and group records, 1850 1923; 1850-1923; 20 Files; (13 volumes, 7 folders)
  This series contains the operational records of church groups and non-governing church committees. Also included in the series are records relating to the church's Sunday school.
  - Society for Parish Affairs and Business, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Porter Female Association records, 1850 1885; 1850-1885 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  - Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1886 1900; 1886-1900 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Woman's Missionary Society records, 1874 1880; 1874-1880 (Box 1, Volume 18)
  - Woman's Missionary Society records, 1880 1887; 1880-1887 (Box 1, Volume 19)
  - Woman's Missionary Society records, 1887 1891; 1887-1891 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Woman's Missionary Society records, 1891 1899; 1891-1899 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Woman's Missionary Society records, 1894 1904; 1894-1904 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Constitution and by-laws of the sunday school, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Young People's Society record book, 1878 1884; 1878-1884 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  - Young People's Society, 1882 1891; 1882-1891 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Adult Department certificate, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Church Work Committee financial records, 1887 1892; 1887-1892 (Box 1, Volume 13)
  - Church Work Committee financial records, 1893 1915; 1893-1915 (Box 1, Volume 14)
  - Church work committee reports and reciepts, 1893 1918; 1893-1918 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Records of the Church Work Committee, 1893 1904; 1893-1904 (Box 1, Volume 15)
  - Records of the Church Work Committee, 1904 1914; 1904-1914 (Box 1, Volume 16)
  - Records of the Church Work Committee, 1914 1923; 1914-1923 (Box 1, Volume 17)
  - Sunday school library catalogue, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lessons in Sacred Music for Sabbath Schools, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Ministerial records and church services, 1800 1950; 1800-1950; 11 Folders
  This series contains records relating to ministers, the installation of ministers, and special church services. Included in the series are orders of worship for special anniversaries, dedications, and installations, correspondence with potential interim pastors, obituary poems, and a hymn manuscript.
  - Leach family papers and photographs, 1800 1804; 1800, 1804 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Obituary poems, 1831 1855; 1831-1834, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Packard family legal and financial records, 1838 1842; 1838-1842 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Ministerial correspondence, 1850 1852; 1850-1852 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Pulpit supply, 1850 1869; 1850-1854, 1868-1869 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dedication services, 1851 1924; 1851-1924 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Installation services, 1852 1948; 1852-1948 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - David Howard correspondence, 1871 1872; 1871-1872 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Orders of worship, 1874 1950; 1874-1950 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Rev. Z. T. Sullivan photograph, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Hymn composed by Dan Huntington, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)